FAHAD GUMA

ICT Software Developer

Email: jifahcas@gmail.com/ fahad.guma.2019@gmail.com

Tel: +256 785532537 / +256 702598021

Am a versatile ICT Software Developer with 4 years of experience in designing, developing, testing and managing software applications and internal frameworks while evaluating operating system feasibility and always committed to technological advancement. Specializes in HTML5/CSS3, JavaScript and responsive design, Mobile-Web development and database management.

Work Experience

International Institute of Tropical Agriculture (IITA-Uganda): June 2019 – Dec 2020

ICT Software Developer – UNDP-UGVS Volunteer/Intern.

Summary of roles and responsibilities

- Refined and updated two ICT-based decision support tools for disseminating knowledge on Climate Smart Agriculture to coffee farmers in Uganda.
- Developed the Shade Tree Advice Smartphone Application from the phase 1 web-based Shade Tree Advice Tool
- Validated and cleaned data from central and east regions and populated it in the Shade
 Tree Advice Smartphone application
- Contributed technical input to the development of data collection protocols and tools for the ranking survey in northern Uganda
- Testing the tool with public and private extension and adapting the tool
- Incorporation of Shade Tree Advice Tool in the Stepwise Application
- Contributed technical input in the Stepwise Impact Assessment design, protocol and tool development
- Conducted and participated in the Shade Tree Ranking survey in northern Uganda region
- Conducted and participated in 3 quarterly monitoring of Stepwise Impact Study assessments in Luweero district.
- Worked with other CGIAR partners on the development of Technical report on the recommendations for hosting and continued maintenance of Shade Tree Advice Tool and sub-tools.
- Contributed to 16 IITA Hub monthly reports, 2 annual 3 semi-annual and 2 quarterly donor (USAID) technical reports.

- Contributed to the writing of 5 field trip reports for Climate Smart Agriculture program.
- Contributed to resource mobilization including the joint development of research proposals and concepts.

Google Africa Developer Scholarship (GADS) Cohort 2: April 2020 – Dec 2020 Mobile Web Specialist (MWS) Software Engineer

Summary of roles and responsibilities

- Creating accounts on all program channels; Slack workspace, Facebook group and Plural sight Platform-Mobile Web Specialist career path Channel.
- Joining and forming teams on Mobile Web Specialist career path on Slack Channel
- Adding GADS calendar to channel calendar to be updated on all Online sessions
- Watch and attend 10+ hours of content and score 100+ average over 2/3 MWS Skill IQ assessments during learning phase 1
- Watch and attend 20+ hours of content and score 180+ average over 2/3 MWS Skill IQ assessments during learning phase 2
- Complete role specific project; Album Store Product Page during project phase.

SyncMedia Monitoring and Research Company (U) Itd.: March 2018 – May 2019 **Computer End User-support and IT Systems Support**

Summary of roles and responsibilities

- Installing and configuring computer hardware, software, systems, networks, printers and scanners
- Monitoring and maintaining computer systems and networks in house and remotely
- Provided technical input for the continued development and internal pretesting of the Sync Media monitoring systems with other Software Developers
- Compile weekly media monitoring reports from the team that contribute to monthly clients reports and annual reports
- Contribute to resource mobilization with the team through development of business proposals that are presented to various clients

- Responding in a timely manner to service issues and requests from the team and clients
- Providing technical support across the company both hardware and software
- Setting up accounts for new users and account user management
- Repairing and replacing equipment as necessary
- Training junior staff members on the use of the Sync Media Monitoring systems.
- Engage with Sync Media ICT Communication platform and identify synergies and potential partnerships that resulted in business clients for the company.

SyncMedia Monitoring and Research Company (U) Itd.: Oct 2017 – Feb 2018 ICT Deployment Officer

Summary of roles and responsibilities

- Setting up regional computer systems for recording upcountry stations.
- Deploying regional software onto the hardware computers and all attached devices in upcountry regions in the country.
- Establishing connection between the regional computer systems with the main server at the main station in Kampala.
- Training upcountry users, on the use of regional computer systems
- Monitoring and maintenance of the regional computer systems from the main duty station in Kampala remotely.
- Occasionally deploying software updates on the regional computer systems.

AfroSoft IT Solutions (U) ltd: June 2016 – August 2016 Industrial

Training – ICT Software Developer Intern.

Summary of roles and responsibilities

- Software development; complete development of Android Game Application
- Systems administration and IT support; Creating user accounts and user management
- Linux & Unix Administration; Executing Linux commands and scripts on server machines
- Dynamic website development; Complete development of personal Portfolio website
- Database management (MYSQL& SQL); complete development of school library MYSQL database on phpMyAdmin Apache server and managing data.
- Hardware and software maintenance; Assembling and dissembling of Hardware
- Graphics designing; designing logos and badges for Android Game Application
- Networking administration; terminating Ethernet cable and configuring LAN locally

• Report writing and documentation; Complete end of training Project Report and Technical Design report for the Android Game Application.

Skills and Abilities

- Designing and development of data collection protocols and tools for Climate Smart Agriculture activities
- Software programming skills in HTML/CSS, JavaScript, PhP, MySQL, Java
- Computer literacy: competent in using Microsoft word, Excel, PowerPoint and Access
- Teleworking skills: capable of using online meeting platforms such as Zoom, Skype, Microsoft Teams and Google Classroom.
- Data entry skills of Stepwise Impact Study experiments
- Data interpretation and presentation
- Proposal and Project report writing skills
- Work planning and Budgeting

Education background

MAKERERE UNIVERSITY: 2013 - 2017

Bachelor's Degree of Science in Software Engineering

AfroSoft IT Solutions (U) Itd: June 2016 – August 2016

Certificate in Internship and Industrial Training in IT and ICT Software development

Nyakasura School: 2011 – 2012

Uganda Advanced Certificate of Education (U.A.C.E)

Nyakusura School: 2007 – 2010

Uganda Certificate of Education (U.C.E)

Kahungabunyonyi Primary School: 2000 – 2006

Primary Leaving Examination (P.L.E)

References

Name: Ms. Diana Kirungi

Title: Research Associate - Gender, IITA

Email: D.Kirungi@cgiar.org

Tel: +256 781 735859

Name: Mr. David Mukasa

Title: Research Associate – Agronomist, IITA

Email: <u>D.Mukasa@cgiar.org</u>

Tel: +256 772 444917

Name: Ms. Susan Mukasa

Title: Operations Director - SyncMedia Ltd

Email: smukasa@syncmedia.co.ug